Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Prints from the Works Progress Administration, Federal Art Project 1935-1943 PR 345
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of prints from the Works Progress Administration, Federal Art Project
1935-1943
New-York Historical Society
Federal Art Project
PR 345
3.5 Linear feet in one box and two flat file folders
The collection includes 22 prints produced by 17 artists in connection with the Works Progress Administration's Federal Art Project (1935-1943), specifically from New York City.
Accruals Note
Additional related prints may be acquired by purchase or donation in the future and added to the collection.
Arrangement Note
The collection is arranged by artist name.
Biographical/Historical Note
The Federal Art Project (1935-1943) was a Depression-era relief program run by the Works Progress Administration. The art project employed thousands of artists across the United States to create paintings, murals, photographs, and other art forms for the public. This collection includes a relatively small number of the thousands of "portable" works, specifically prints from New York City, created during the program.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition Note
The prints were purchased over time by N-YHS. Dates for each are noted in the container list.
Related Archival Materials Note
This collection holds only prints created under the auspices of the Federal Art Project. Some of the artists included here can also be found in other N-YHS collections unrelated to the Federal Art Project. See N-YHS's Department of Prints, Photographs and Architectural Collections' Printmaker File (PR 58).
Scope and Contents
The collection includes 22 prints produced by 17 artists in connection with the Works Progress Administration's Federal Art Program, specifically from New York City. The specific artists and works included in the collection are detailed in the container list. Generally, the works focus on people, rather than structures or landscapes, in urban settings such as street scenes, getting tattoos, street cart sales, recreation, laborers, and searching through a garbage can.
Lithographs.; Prints (visual works).; Woodcuts (prints); New York (N.Y.) -- Pictorial works.; Abramovitz, Albert, 1879-1963; Barlow, Lou, 1908-2011; Berman, Sarah, 1895-1957; Botts, Hugh, 1903-1964; Burke, David, active mid 20th century; Dwight, Mabel; Eichenberg, Fritz, 1901-1990; Feinstein, David, active 1935-1943; Gottlieb, Harry, 1895-1992; Jacobi, Eli, 1898-1984; Mandelman, Beatrice; Markham, Kyra; Miller, Grambs; Nooney, Ann, 1900-1970; Parish, Betty Waldo, 1910-1986; Schardt, Bernard P., 1904-1979; Velonis, Anthony, 1911-1997
- Abramovitz, Albert (1879-1963), circa 1935-1943 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Includes linocut Rickets (circa 1935-1943), number 7 of 25 for the NYC-WPA. Signed in pencil. Stamped. Purchase, November 2019.
- Barlow, Lou (1908-2011), 1936 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents Note
  Includes wood engraving Sweet Potato Man (1936). Purchased 1983.
- Berman, Sarah (1895-1957), circa 1936-1942 (Box 1)
  Includes lithograph Harlem Street Scene (circa 1936-1942). Purchase, November 2015.
- Botts, Hugh (1903-1964), 1937 (Box 1)
  Includes: etching East River (1937), number 22. Signed in pencil. Stamped. Purchase, November 2015; aquatint Clinic (circa 1935-1943), number 5 of edition of 25. Signed in pencil. Stamped. Purchase, November 2019.
- Burke, David, 1935 (Box 1)
  Includes color screenprint Going to Work (1935), number 2. Signed in pencil. Stamped. Purchase, November 2015.
- Dwight, Mabel (1876-1955), 1936, 1939 (Box 1)
  Includes: lithograph Buried Treasure (1939), number 20, signed in pencil, stamped, purchased November 2016; General Seminary (1936),signed in pencil (no stamp), purchased October 2017.
- Eichenberg, Fritz (1901-1990), 1935-1943 (Box 1)
  Includes wood engraving Lumber Yard (1935-1943), number 11, signed in pencil, stamped. Purchase, October 2017.
- Feinstein, David, circa 1935-1943 (Box 1)
  Includes lithograph The Boss, signed in pencil, stamped. Purchase November 2019.
- Gottlieb, Harry (1895-1992), 1936/1939 (Folder FF-1)
  Includes lithograph Drydock. Edition of 25 made for NYC-WPA, with stamp. Signed in pencil, titled in lower margin. Purchase, January 2019.
- Grambs, Blanche (1916-2010), circa 1935-1943 (Box 1)
  Includes drypoint Cold, number 16, for the NYC-WPA, signed in pencil (B.M. Grambs), stamped. Artist later known as Grambs Miller. Purchase, October 2018.
- Jacobi, Eli (1898-1984), circa 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  Includes lithograph Tattoo Artist (ca. 1936-1939), depicting the interior of Apache Harry's tattoo shop at 22 Bowery. Signed in pencil, stamped. Purchase, 2016.
- Mandelman, Beatrice (1912-1998), circa 1936-1941 (Box 1)
  Includes lithograph Shave 25 Cents, signed in pencil, stamped partially erased. Purchase, November 2019.
- Markham, Kyra (1891-1967), 1936-1937 (Box 1)
  Includes: lithograph The Flies at Minsky's (1936), signed in pencil, stamped, purchased October 2018; lithograph Stage Door Johnnie (1937), number 11, signed in pencil, stamped, purchased November 2019.
- Nooney, Ann (1900-1970), circa 1935 (Box 1)
  Includes lithograph Fulton Street, Brooklyn (circa 1935), number 9, signed in pencil, stamped. Purchase, November 2015.
- Nooney, Ann (1900-1970), circa 1936-1939 (Folder FF-2)
  Two lithographs: Demolition with Water Tower, NYC, signed and titled in pencil (Purchase, November 2019); Music in the Park, signed and titled in pencil (Purchase, November 2019).
- Parish, Betty Waldo (1910-1986), 1936-1939 (Box 1)
  Includes wood engraving Our Lady of Pompeii (or "Church of Pompeii"). Signed in pencil, stamp on reverse. Purchase, January 2019.
- Schardt, Bernard P. (1904-1979), 1936/1939 (Box 1)
  Includes wood engraving Women's Court, Jefferson Market. Signed (B.P. Schardt) and titled in pencil, stamped. Purchase, January 2019.
- Velonis, Anthony (1911-1997), 1938 (Box 1)
  Includes serigraph, mounted to support sheet 6:30 P.M. Edition of 25 made for NYC-WPA, with stamp. Signed, titled, dated, and annotated "Working proof on illustration board." Purchase, January 2019.